Daiei Productions Presents
YOKIHI
Produced by Masaichi Nagata,
Run Run Shaw
Screenplay by Matsutaro Kawaguchi,
Yoshikata Yoda, Masashige Narusawa
Cinematography by Kohei Sugiyama
Sound by Kunio Hashimoto
Art Direction by Hiroshi Mizutani
Historical Research by Lu Shi-hou
Music by Fumio Hayasaka
Cast
Yang Yu-huan/Kuei-fei - Machiko Kyo
Emperor Hsüan-tsung - Masayuki Mori
An Lu-shan - So Yamamura
Kao Li-hsi - Eitaro Shindo
Yang Chao/Kuo-chung - Sakae Ozawa
Princess Yen-chun - Haruko Sugimura
Hung-tao - Yoko Minamida
Chen Hsuan-li - Bontaro Miyake
Premier Li Lin-fu - Tatsuya Ishiguro
Yang Hsien - Isao Yamagata
Directed by Kenji Mizoguchi
- We have come to take you away, sire
- Please make yourself ready
Where are you taking me?
- To the Palace of the West, sire
- What?
The Palace of the West?
You're going to confine me there?
- Yes, sire
- No!
I refuse to leave here
I shall remain here
Here, at least I can listen
to the sounds of the city...
...and there are many distractions
to console me in my solitude
Go tell the Emperor that
Tell my son...
...not to cause his old father
any further suffering
But it is the Emperor's order
We must carry out his imperial order
to the letter
Please, make yourself ready to leave
You insult me!
Get out!
Out!
Kuei-fei...
Where are you, my love?
Are you watching over me
from somewhere beyond the grave?
Alas, I am too old now...
... for any pleasures
this world may offer me
I wish only to see you again
Any place without your presence...
... is unbearable to me
Kuei-fei...
... where are you?
Well done.
You all played very well
I wasn't too sure of the piece at first...
...but I very much enjoyed your rendition
I think it is one of Your Majesty's
masterpieces
However, there is a certain
underlying sadness to it, sire
How can you expect me to compose
anything joyous, the way I feel?
Majesty, you are the most
fortunate person in the Empire
Look at me, do I really
seem that fortunate?
Fortune is not a mere corollary
of one's social status
If I were truly fortunate...
...then I would be able to compose
more joyous pieces of music
This piece was composed
in honour of my late wife
Well... let us play the next movement
Your Majesty...
...Premier Li wishes
for an audience with you...
...to discuss pressing affairs of state
And as your schedule
must be strictly observed...
...I must ask you kindly
to finish now for today
Thank you, everybody
Wait
I just want to try this last piece
Premier Li, you can wait a little longer
I fear I cannot, Majesty
Besides myself, you are to address
several foreign ambassadors, sire
We also have to plan
your journey details
Affairs of state must always
take precedence, sire
You constantly interfere
with my pleasures...
...and bind me to ridiculous
schedules and ceremonies!
You distract His Majesty
from his duties of governance
Get out!
- Majesty...
- What is it?
Please look at this statue
of the Bodhisattva...
...that came in tribute
from the Silla Kingdom of Korea
She is truly a work of great beauty
And who is this?
You honour me
by giving her recognition, Majesty
I have taken the liberty of selecting
this highly capable lady...
...to take care of all your needs, sire
It's unnecessary
Nobody can take the place
of the late Empress
Just forget about it
I heard that His Majesty
turned her down
Did he refuse you?
It wasn't your fault
We may be the most beautiful
women in the capital...
...but we're just not beautiful enough
for His Imperial Majesty, that's all!
You just have to accept your fate
with good grace
Oh, welcome, sire!
General An Lu-shan has arrived!
Welcome
Oh, welcome, sire
What a shame. I really thought
your daughter would be accepted
She failed, despite all your intercessions
on our behalf
What a shame
That's put an end
to all our plans, General
Not so. All is not lost yet
Her acceptance would have
hastened things along, that's all
All our hopes are dashed
She's the third sister to be rejected
I'll end up working here
and never getting on in life
General, please take me with you
to your fortress
- And what would you do there?
- But I've no future here in the capital
I'd rather be an official under you,
General...
...then I could take bribes
and get rich quick!
You sound desperate,
and I don't hire such desperate men
I'll worry about it later.
General, let's have a drink
- Good
- Come right this way
- Let's drink
- You go on ahead...
What's up with you? Look lively!
Master Kao will be arriving soon.
Let's go
Even on the branches of the willows
Throughout the town...
Hey, the guests have arrived!
Stop that singing!
- Who is she?
- She's my youngest cousin
Same family as the others?
She's their half-sister. A country girl,
just arrived from the mountains
- General?
- Wait...
So, you're a daughter
of the Yang family?
I'm more like their servant
Hey!
Show me your face
Please leave me alone,
I have work to do
Hey!
What are you doing?
What are you doing to me?
What...?
You're quite a beauty
Let go of me!
You're wasted here in the kitchen
General! What are you doing
in this place?
- I've just found a real treasure
- What?
This one, here!
That was a real shame
your daughter was rejected
No, not at all, one can't expect
the daughter of a mere restaurateur...
...to attract the attention of His Majesty
It was our fault for thinking
above our station
What do you mean, brother,
that it was our fault?
You want to run this restaurant
for the rest of your life?
Well, I don't! I want to be someone
and get on in life!
I just think differently from you
You want to use your daughters
to further your own ambitions
What's wrong with that? I'm doing it
for the honour of the Yang Family
For the prosperity of the whole family
I'm only doing the right thing
No, your motives are evil...
Stop
- Let me see how you look in these
- No!
Don't answer back! Put them on quickly!
If I put those on,
everyone will just laugh at me!
What a child! Come here
I'm just a country peasant
Since my mother died, I've been forced
to work as a maid in the kitchens
You treat me worse than a dog!
Everyone has to start somewhere
Take me for instance, my father
was a foreigner in this country
I suffered enormous prejudice
and was maltreated as a child
But human beings have a destiny...
...and if you don't grasp at good fortune
then you'll regret it for life
Don't you see, you have been presented
with a wonderful opportunity?
Right then, try these robes on
And then what?
We're going to see
where your destiny lies
You've never realised
how beautiful you are?
No, not at all
Well, it's up to me
to convince you otherwise
But you must be aware of your beauty,
before you can convince others to see it
Yes?
Get dressed quickly
Follow the General's kind advice
and put this robe on
Others may envy us...
...but our low birth stops us
from progressing further
Is it only the Li family
that can gain advancement?
There's nothing we can do
about it for the present
No one can stand in the way
of Premier Li Lin-fu
It's unfortunate the Emperor
wasn't attracted to your daughter
He can't forget the late Empress
Wu-hui, can he?
She was a wonderful Empress
There could be no other like her
in this world
Yes, there could be, Master Kao!
There could be another Wu-hui!
You're not the only one who wishes
to see Empress Wu-hui reincarnated
Those who support the Emperor
wish it, too
- Another Empress Wu-hui, you say?
- Yes, another. See for yourself
It's Yu-huan, isn't it?
She's beautiful
You're such fools!
How could you hide such a jewel
in your kitchens?
Who is this?
My youngest cousin, Yu-huan
From here, we're heading
for the convent on Mount Li
I will ask the Mother Abbess
to present you to His Majesty's court
She is a relative of the Emperor
and he trusts her implicitly
Master Kao is already there
waiting for us
At last, our luck is going to change
I have no doubt that you will attract
the Emperor's attention
As a reward for finding you...
...I will be called back to the capital
in triumph and made a minister
And as the highest ranking concubine,
you shall enjoy a most glorious life
You must take full advantage
of the fact that you were born beautiful
What's wrong?
Why are you so quiet?
Don't you understand,
if you become an imperial concubine...
...great status and honour
will be bestowed upon all your family?
And I will simply become a tool
for the family to use...
...just as I was when I was forced
to work in their kitchens
Not at all!
This is for your own happiness
Our rewards will be
a mere fraction of yours
You must understand that
Everything will turn out just fine...
Just fine
So, from this point onwards...
...everything about your past
will be extinguished
What do you think of her,
Mother Abbess?
A lovely girl
- Everything is prepared, madam
- This girl is your servant
She will obey your every whim
Please allow me
to show you to your room
Do you think she will be
to the Emperor's liking?
Mother Abbess...
Just as you recommended Wu-hui
as a wife for the Emperor...
...I would like to propose her suitability
as an imperial consort
Do you think the Emperor trusts you
more than he does me?
I'm not saying that at all. I mean...
Master Kao...
...do you have any idea how much
the Emperor trusts my judgement?
- Of course I do, but...
- Then be silent!
Yes, madam
It was I who instructed
the Empress Wu-hui
And I will mould this girl
in the same way
You will see, I will make her
worthy of the Emperor
Yes, madam
His Majesty has arrived
He's walking in the Plum Tree Garden
I've been told to fetch you,
it's time for you to meet him
Do you think I'll be all right
dressed like this?
You look very beautiful
If I am not to the Emperor's liking...
...I'll end up being confined
to his harem...
...to live out the rest of my days
You mustn't concern yourself
with such things
I think the Emperor will be amazed
when he sees how beautiful you are
What kind of a man is the Emperor?
What kind of things does he like?
How did Wu-hui manage
to capture his heart?
Please tell me
The Emperor is a very
kind-hearted person
And he greatly appreciates
people who show sincerity
The more you listen to his music,
the more you will understand him
I see...
It is time for you to take some tea,
Majesty
I'm enjoying looking at the plum
blossoms, I don't want any tea
But your physician has given
strict instructions, Majesty
Why do you all constantly
try to impede me?
You don't even allow me
to enjoy my leisure as I wish
Please do not chastise me, Majesty...
...I am simply following
the strict rules of court etiquette
Please, if you would kindly make
your way to the tea house...
Your Majesty...
Even in the distance,
the plum blossoms look so beautiful
It's not only the plum blossom
that is beautiful...
...there is also a beautiful girl
in full blossom, Majesty
I would like to express the colour and
scent of the plum blossoms in music
I would like to be left alone
this evening, please
Thank you. You may go now
You are dismissed
Master Kao, why are you still here?
Your Majesty, I understand your grief
at the loss of Empress Wu-hui...
...but to continue mourning her
like this...
I'm in no mood to listen
to your sermons this evening
I asked you to leave me alone
this evening. Understand?
Yes, sire
I would like to be left alone
to reminisce about my late Empress
Who are you?
Who allowed you
into my private chambers?
I know...
This must be Kao's doing
Because I talk so much of my late wife...
...he has taken it upon himself
to bring me a woman who looks like her
Your resemblance to Wu-hui is uncanny
However, it is not her body
that I yearn for, but her spirit
Majesty...
No one can replace Wu-hui
Please don't destroy my memories
I wish you to go now
Isn't that the piece I composed
in the Plum Tree Garden?
You play very well
Very well indeed
Did you learn to play that piece
to impress me?
Or did you play it simply
to show me how clever you are?
Not at all, Your Majesty
Why did you play it, then?
I merely wanted to soothe and comfort
your poor heart, Majesty...
...if only for a short moment
My poor heart?
Majesty...
...I did not enter your court
of my own free will
Others will be delighted
if my presence here pleases you
It has nothing to do with me...
...it is the will of those
that brought me here
I am like their puppet
and they pull my strings
I thought I'd have to spend
the rest of my life here...
...like some ornament
at Your Majesty's side
There was nothing I could do but
accept the inevitability of my destiny
But then...
...when I realised how much love
Your Majesty still felt for Wu-hui...
...I felt ashamed of myself
Empress Wu-hui was
a very fortunate person indeed
I never imagined...
...that a woman
could be so loved by a man
I envy Wu-hui
If only I could meet a man who was
as gentle and kind as Your Majesty...
...then I would be happy
I shall take my leave of you, sire
Wait a moment
Up until now, I believed only Wu-hui
could bring happiness into my life
But you...
...of your own accord,
played my composition...
...and gave me great comfort
Moreover,
you have asked for no reward
Above all...
...you spoke to me with honesty,
as you would address any other person
Not even Wu-hui
was ever able to do that
Tell me what your name is
I am Yu-huan of the Yang family,
Your Majesty
Yu-huan, from now on
I wish you to remain close at my side...
...as a friend
Only if you wish, of course
Yes, sire
I would like that very much
That settles it.
You agree to stay at my side?
I take that as a promise
Tomorrow morning...
...I want you to prepare the hot spring
in the Lotus Pool for Yu-huan
Lady Yu-huan...
...since Empress Wu-hui passed away...
...you are the first to have been
allowed to use the Lotus Pool
His Majesty says that spring
has returned to the court!
I can't stay long.
I have to leave tomorrow
It's unfortunate that I have to return
to my old life as a provincial governor...
...without seeing how
Yu-huan is getting along
Does my presence here
embarrass you?
Please, General...
...a governorship is an honourable post
What use is a provincial governorship?
I want a position in the capital
If Li Lin-fu falls from power,
who will be the next premier?
Do you have your sights
set on being premier, General?
One must be ambitious and aim high,
for the premiership...
...or even the imperial throne!
The throne?
You just watch, your little kitchen help
may one day become Empress
You're right...
Anything is possible
I will never abandon my ambitions
If Yu-huan becomes influential,
you won't remain here much longer
General, it seems she's already
been accepted as his mistress
Being one of his harem means nothing
The important thing is for Yu-huan
to rise above the other women in status
The future of the Yang family
depends on it
Don't forget that, Chao!
In accordance with the law, sire,
it is dictated that Lady Cheng must die
I have no recollection
of issuing such an order
You are the servants of a prisoner!
How dare you presume to speak
in front of His Imperial Majesty!
Get out!
Out!
It is strictly forbidden by imperial
decree for any lady in your harem...
...to involve herself
in matters of governance
Therefore the penalty
for such a crime is death
But Lady Cheng only involved herself
in politics...
...because she wanted to secure
a government post for her relative
I am only observing a law that
you yourself decreed, Your Majesty
But laws should be made to safeguard
the well-being of the people
Why can't you use the law
for the benefit of the people?
If Your Majesty should care
to make such laws...
...then I will faithfully carry them out
However, I must insist that if a law...
Enough!
I have no wish to listen to you
Your Majesty...
I thought that you had the power
to do anything that you wished
For years, I was able to do
as I pleased in all matters
But the laws and codes of practice
that I myself made now constrain me...
...and the result
is a curtailment of my powers
Sometimes it is important to relax
and forget all your troubles
Forget all my troubles?
Let me accompany you, Your Majesty
- Where to?
- Into the city
This evening there is an annual festival,
and the whole city will be celebrating
Festival of Lanterns
Hold on to me tightly
so I don't lose you, sire
There are servants from the court
approaching
This way
That was a narrow escape
Is it all right to remove my hood?
It's so uncomfortable
I'm sure we'll be fine here
- How kind of you, sire
- These are for me?
Many thanks. Please, accept these
Won't you try one?
Try it
Tonight, you must do
exactly as I tell you
It's delicious, isn't it?
I'm not sure
Everybody is so kind
This is the first time in a long time
that I've felt so free
Aren't you glad you ventured out?
These sweets are very tasty
Now you see!
We can't allow a pair of lovers
to pass through
- Why not?
- You have to drink before you can pass
- I don't want to trouble you
- You're not troubling us! Have a drink!
Please forgive their impertinence
Let's celebrate your wedding!
- One more!
First we drink, then we dance!
Your dancing was wonderful
Why did you never
dance for me before?
Well, it was the beautiful sound of
your lute that made me want to dance
Your movements kept perfect timing
Only because Your Majesty
matched my tempo
I've had a marvellous evening
I feel so refreshed
that my blood is tingling
It makes me so happy
to hear you say that
This evening, I don't feel
like an emperor...
...I feel like a man of the people,
you can call me Li San-lan!
Me, too. I'm Yu-huan,
just a simple peasant girl
Majesty...
May we have some tea, please?
Careful, it's hot
Here
You know...
...it feels like I've lived here
with you for years and years!
As our governor-generals, it is your
responsibility to defend our borders...
...against the invading barbarians
For a long time they have been
troublesome and war seems inevitable
But it is important to win them over
not by force but by diplomacy
It will all depend on your abilities
His Majesty is relying on you
completely, generals...
...and each of you is expected
to fulfil his duty
I hope you enjoy this gathering...
...that His Majesty has arranged
in your honour
Well, if it isn't General An Lu-shan...
Welcome to the capital
Well, Chao...
You must call me by the new name
and title that His Majesty gave me
So, you're Minister Yang Kuo-chung
now, are you?
Close to the throne.
A lofty position indeed
Damn these upstart women!
They live in luxury,
all paid for with our taxes
They're just taking advantage
of His Majesty's love for Kuei-fei
They're jumped-up servants who think
they're better than the rest of us
Make way for Her Ladyship! Move!
Move!
Move, you bastard!
What do you think you're doing?
What are you doing?
The Yang family has corrupted
the whole court!
Death to the Yangs!
Don't just stand there!
Quickly, to the palace!
Kill them!
- Death to the Yangs!
- Kill them all!
- Down with the Yangs!
- Kill them!
Kill the Yangs!
- What's happened?
- What's happened, madam?
On the way here,
we were attacked by a mob...
...and they were shouting,
"Death to the Yang family!"
How frightening for you
How dare they treat friends
of His Majesty this way!
They're ruffians!
Were they arrested?
Our guards just stood by
and watched them abuse us!
You were all useless! Someone must
take responsibility for this!
I apologise, madam.
What were the guards doing?
Are you all right, madam?
What about Kuei-fei?
What happened?
Kuei-fei...
Are you hurt?
You were right when you said
one should be ambitious and aim high
And you have been made
governor of three provinces
You must be pleased
with your progress
That's nothing compared
to your promotion, Minister
And to whom do you attribute
your success?
I attribute it to my own prowess
It certainly hasn't been easy, though
Don't talk nonsense!
It's all due to Kuei-fei
And Kuei-fei, in turn,
owes all she has to me!
Listen, Chao...
Promote me to a central government
post and make me a minister
Only the Emperor has the authority
to do that, not me
So arrange for Kuei-fei
to make a request to His Majesty
It is forbidden for women
to have any involvement in politics
Listen to me, Chao...
...I have now consolidated
my power base in the north
You'd be wise to retain my friendship
if you wish to remain in power
- Minister?
- What is it?
Would you ask His Majesty what music
he'd like the musicians to play next?
I will consider what
you have just said, General
Does Your Majesty have any
particular music you'd like to hear next?
Let me see...
I know...
...in honour of my new governors...
...I shall play for them myself
It has been a long time, madam
Congratulations on your new post,
General
I don't see it as any cause
for celebration
I still nurture my ambition
for a government post in the capital
Yu-huan...
Listen to me...
You have become
a very influential concubine at court
I want to be a government minister...
...and I have the right to expect
your help on this matter
General, please... not here
What?
So, you won't even deign
to listen to what I have to say?
Are you too selfish
to think of anyone but yourself?
Look how your three sisters
have risen through the ranks
Even Chao has been rewarded
with a ministerial post
Why, then, must I languish
in the provinces?
Please don't raise your voice
- Excuse me
- Wait!
You really are exquisitely beautiful
I never thought
you could look this radiant
If only I had taken you for my own
that day we first met...
...both our destinies
would be very different now
Yu-huan...
What are you doing?
I belong to the Emperor now
What do you mean,
"belong to the Emperor"?
You mustn't forget, Yu-huan...
...it was I who took you away
from the drudgery of life in the kitchen
And has His Majesty not generously
rewarded you for your efforts?
Some reward, indeed!
Yu-huan...
Surely you've heard that the people
are cursing the Yang family?
Do you not see how the nation suffers
under a heavy taxation system...
...while Chao abuses his position
and lines his own pockets?
And your three sisters lead a life
of ostentatious decadence
The people may revolt
at any moment...
...and when they do,
it'll be the Yang family they'll be after
If it goes on like this, even
the Emperor's life may be in danger
Even the Emperor was once
nothing more than a provincial warlord
Fortune favours the mighty...
...and any mighty feudal lord
can make himself Emperor!
Listen, Yu-huan...
My future is as boundless as an ocean
Why don't you accompany me
to my fortress?
This is the only way
you can save yourself now
Kuei-fei!
Kuei-fei, His Majesty
has finished his recital now
But why are you telling me this
all of a sudden? Tell me the reason
The whole nation seems to be burning
with rage at the Yang family
Please let me return
to my former life as Yu-huan...
...and discharge my cousin Kuo-chung
and my three sisters from the court
Your three sisters
are of no consequence
And as for promoting Kuo-chung
to a ministerial position...
...I have my own ulterior motive
for doing that
I would never be foolish enough
to allow my feelings for you...
...to jeopardise the governance
of the country
I'm not thinking of just
Your Majesty's safety...
...but for the safety
of the whole country
Wait!
Kuei-fei...
...I am sure that you are aware
of the consequences...
...if a consort involves herself
in the affairs of the state
Of course I am aware, sire
Therefore, please punish me
as you see fit
Are you saying that you have
no compunction about leaving me?
Perhaps I have committed a crime...
...and I am no longer worthy
of the title of consort
Are you so willing to listen to what
others have to say rather than me?
The other evening...
...the whole court knew that
you were talking alone with An Lu-shan
Majesty, you must trust me, please
But you are still determined
to leave me?
Please forgive me!
Enough!
Master Kao!
Take Kuei-fei
to the harem immediately
But Your Majesty...
Do as I command!
Premier Li... what is it you want?
Majesty...
I heard that you have
dismissed Kuei-fei
I must say, Your Majesty, that I admire
your decision and congratulate you
Is that all you came to say?
Yes, sire
Kuo-chung, I hear you've been taking
advantage of my illness...
...and have been acting
as though you were the Premier
All with the blessing of His Majesty
Surely you should be
considering retirement
You're too infirm to deal
with the pressures of being Premier
I'll see that you receive notification
of discharge of your duties
I won't hear such insolence!
Silence!
Your Majesty, Kuei-fei refused
to enter the harem...
...but went to the house
of her cousin Yang Hsien
What?
It's unacceptable for such
a noble lady of the court...
...to stay in the house of a commoner
On your orders, I shall go and find her
We will bring her back immediately, sire
I'm so glad that
you have come back here
It's better for your sisters
and for Chao as well
You can remain here
as long as you wish
I will protect you with my life
But what are your plans for the future?
I wish to become Yu-huan once again
You rose too high too quickly...
...that was your misfortune
There are many and varied ways...
... to live a good life
The province where I was born...
... is where I yearn to return
As they hang on the frame
over the door...
... the grapes are ripening
The sun is high in the sky...
When did you arrive here
from the provinces?
- Last year
- Really?
- Do you like it here?
- Yes
Kuei-fei, what are you doing
in such a filthy place?
Master Kao and I have come
to take you back to the palace
I wish to see no one
But the Emperor himself has sent us
His Majesty ordered us
to bring you back immediately
Please get ready
as quickly as possible
Your palanquin is waiting
I will not go back
I prefer to stay here
This is all your fault, Hsien
You should be worried
about your own future!
The people of Chang'an
are after your blood!
It's impossible for a politician
to please everyone
Consider how you have lorded it
over the whole nation
You should resign from your post.
It is her wish also
What do you know about anything?
She is concerned for you!
Don't be so insolent!
- You damn upstart!
- What?
Someone help me!
What insolence!
We cannot just stand by idly
and watch our country fall!
We must destroy the Yang family
and save the empire!
By favouring the Yangs, His Majesty
must also share some of the blame!
It is time to usher in a new era!
The nation must have a new ruler!
Our objective is to take
the capital, Chang'an!
Onwards to the capital!
In an attempt to destroy the Tangs
and usurp the imperial throne...
... General An Lu-shan
heads a revolution
Giving himself the title
Emperor Taien...
... he advances with his army
toward the capital, Chang'an
Learning of the perils now threatening
the life of Emperor Hsüan-tsung...
... Kuei-fei decides
to return to him immediately...
... to be by his side
and face their fate together
Despite the many dangers,
she remains resolute and unafraid
Emperor Hsüan-tsung flees the capital,
and after an arduous journey...
... they rest in Mukuai,
a desolate village
Let me do this for you
You go and see to His Majesty
No, I'll prepare it
He looks exhausted.
Take this to him quickly
Yes, madam
Forgive me, I'm afraid this is all
we can serve you, Majesty
And what about my men?
Aren't they hungry, too?
They'll be fed soon
I see...
No!
What's happening?
Look, men!
We've killed the three Yang sisters!
We've killed each one of them!
The people demanded their execution!
Listen, why did we flee from the capital
without putting up a fight?
We Imperial Guards are a disgrace!
General An's forces are
growing in strength!
Everyone who's anti-government
is joining his ranks!
They're angry with the politicians
Kuo-chung and Kao!
We have no ill-feeling
towards His Imperial Majesty!
It was for His Majesty's sake that
we executed the three Yang sisters!
General An isn't our enemy,
it's the Yang family!
The next to be executed will be
Yang Kuo-chung and Kao Li-hsi!
Commander, we must leave
as soon as the men have eaten
General An has crossed the river
and is advancing on Cheng-Tu
Understood, sir
What are you doing?
Prepare to move out!
What's going on?
It is Premier Yang Kuo-chung
who is to blame for all this
Unless he's punished,
the troops won't move an inch!
Silence! Who's the ringleader?
I want his head!
It's a unanimous decision
We decided to kill the three
Yang sisters as a blood sacrifice
You're powerless
to stand in our way now
- Seize him!
- No... no!
Back, you insolent fools!
Kill Kuo-chung!
Kuei-fei...
I regret having caused you
so much hardship
Being here alone with you...
...it reminds me of that night we spent
during the Festival of Lanterns
The memories are comforting to me
It heartens me
to see you so cheerful, Majesty
It takes a lot more than this
to cause me despair
What is it?
It's terrible
Kuo-chung and the three Yang sisters
were seized by the enemy...
- What?
...and they have been executed
Kuo-chung and the three sisters?
The situation is beyond my control,
Majesty
Please strip me of my title, sire
- What for?
- We are being besieged, sire
Why? Is this a revolt against me?
The army is not disloyal to you, sire
Majesty...
You see... Kuei-fei...
What about Kuei-fei?
Well...
Kuei-fei,
would you leave us a moment...?
Wait! Why can't Kuei-fei
remain here?
Your Majesty, please excuse me
Kuei-fei!
Master Kao, what is it you wish
to tell me without Kuei-fei present?
The executions of Kuo-chung
and the three sisters...
...have not appeased the people
Your Majesty, the soldiers are
demanding the life of Kuei-fei
- What? They want Kuei-fei?
- Yes, sire
Never! Never!
Women of the harem have
no responsibility for affairs of state
However, I have to say that
under the circumstances...
...she is considered a member
of the Yang family, sire
Kao... do you intend to betray us?
Was it not you who recommended
Kuei-fei to me?
And now you intend to kill her?
Majesty... your life is in danger!
We must make a decision
to save you and the nation
Silence! What do you mean,
to save me and the nation?
Have you ever considered
your country before now?
You're just trying to save your own skin!
No, Your Majesty, no!
The soldiers are baying for blood...
...they've lost all reason,
they're going berserk!
Majesty!
What are you doing?
The soldiers are demanding
your life first, Kao!
- What? No!
- You're a traitor and must die!
Forgive me, sire, for spilling blood
in your presence
I will pay the penalty, sire
Never mind about that
I must speak to the troops
Please wait!
- You must hand over Kuei-fei!
- We are loyal to you, sire!
Wait!
Calm yourselves down
Listen to what I have to say...
Kuei-fei!
...Kuei-fei is blameless
Majesty, Kuei-fei
is from the Yang family
Your life is in danger, sire.
It is for your own safety
You must make a decision quickly,
Majesty!
All of you have been
so attentive to me over the years
Pray for the quick restoration of peace
and the return of His Majesty to power
I am praying for the return
of a peaceful springtime...
...when the beautiful plum trees
will once again blossom...
...and people can celebrate
the Festival of Lanterns
I pray with all my heart
that those days arrive soon
Hung-tao...
Please give this to His Majesty from me
Tell him...
...that I shall always and forever
be by his side
- Will you tell him that?
- Yes, madam
- You must come with us
- Prepare yourself!
Let us proceed
Kuei-fei...
Will peace now be restored
to my nation?
After you passed away...
... there was nothing left for me
in this world
General An Lu-shan
soon met his demise...
... but by then...
... my imperial throne
had been usurped...
... by my very own son,
the Crown Prince
He was no different
from An Lu-shan after all
There was never any love
lost between us
What a heartless world we live in
Kuei-fei...
Majesty...
... I have come to take you
away with me
Oh, Kuei-fei?
I have been waiting
for this moment for many years
Finally, the day has come
Give me your hand, Majesty
Let me guide you
I have waited so long for this
We'll be together forever now.
I'll never let you leave my side
Majesty...
no one can ever
tear us asunder this time
Now we can be truly happy
Yes, truly happy
And our happiness shall know no end
I can see you smiling now, my dearest
The End